hello everyone this is Frank defreitis
and welcome to another week of holotalk
and this is a special broadcast because
I'm here in Staten Island
and I'm visiting with John I've
I've who many of you may recognize as
the author of homemade Holograms
and numerous numerous scientific
projects that he has undertaken over the
years how are you today John I'm great
how you doing Frank doing good I see we
have a copy of your book here
I've had this book for ages this is a
first edition I'm hoping to get you to
sign it for me so I can take it back to
my own house
you had told me a little bit earlier an
interesting story about you getting
involved with holography and how the
book came about maybe you could uh
if you don't mind saying that story over
again for the listeners that are
listening around the world to you right
now
well how I started in holography was um
I knew everything about the theory of
holography and I knew about reference
beams and I also realized for my reading
that
if any objects move by half a wavelength
of light we would know when we get a
homogram
so when I knew had all this theoretical
knowledge I didn't think it was
practical for anybody in uh home based
to actually produce a hologram
so as time went on I found out about a
woman Linda lore who was giving
workshops in Long Island and given
workshops and making holography
so I contacted the lender called her up
joined the workshop traveled all the way
out on Long Island
and I went into this class and I seen
this I think I think she called it a
beam it was like look almost like a
crucifix made out of wood that you would
have the laser on one end and and the
film on the other and uh accesses what
is this and she goes well that's what
we're shooting our holograms on
this and I touched it and it didn't
weigh that much and it had a bunch of
little air tubes underneath it and
we went in through the class and we
actually produced the Hologram so it's
just very excited with this information
because I realized I didn't need a
five-ton granite table anymore I didn't
need a two-ton sand table I said this
can be done this can be done so it kind
of compressed it and reduced what what I
needed and from that class I was able to
build like a little home studio
Holograms that's how it began so it
really goes back to my my tutorial class
for win the war so Linda really helped
me out
you also have another book where it was
holography for photographers as well
which I believe you took a lot of the
math out and just presented it as a
step-by-step process so if there's any
photographers out there maybe you'd want
to tell them about that book as well yes
yeah exactly there was a lot of math in
homemade Holograms so a lot of technical
stuff that
if you're learning how to shoot a
picture you really don't need to know
the mechanism of a camera you don't need
to know about shutters you don't need to
know how the lenses work and how the
focus Optics work you could just point
and shoot and with a little experience
you can shoot decent photography
photographs so that was the approach I
took with homemade
photography for photographers I left the
math out and I said okay once you shoot
Holograms and let's just shoot them as
best we can with the smallest amount of
equipment as possible and let it go on
from there and that that was the theory
behind that
[Music]
your background
in science and technology is known by so
many people because of the articles that
you've written over the years all of the
different books that you've put out and
you've got a company here as well images
come
is that correct the images companies
that was yeah tell us about the company
well the the company caters to
um
I guess inquisitive Minds we we we do a
lot of stuff with uh science and
electronics and with holography uh
robotics
it's just uh nuclear uh science or
what's thinking speech recognition
um really have to visit the website and
uh just to say this it's very
Diversified give us a website address
it's
www.imagesco.com so it's imagescode.com
any plans for the future with the
holography or where do you see
holography going for you and and as the
field
well I'm thinking about another book if
I do another book it's really going to
be based towards the student uh for
technology the holography hasn't
expanded hasn't has it really reached a
mass Market never did it we was always
hoping for that to happen that never did
well I think well yeah you know you
could answer that better than I I think
we've been discussing that uh full color
holography hasn't gotten out there
stereograms is still uh a little
difficult to make and still not full
color I think that's that's part of it
and it's not easy I mean it still takes
an amount of setup so but it is
something that artists can approach it's
still like a craft uh that that
they can get into and people can get
into
plan on staying involved with holography
yeah yeah I uh I don't know how active
you know day to day but sure you know I
would never lose
[Music]
it some of it around
yeah well you've built a laser in the
past tell us a little bit about the
helium neon laser and how difficult that
was that that would be an interesting
project for students or someone who even
has their own lab to
or how difficult was that for you
time that I did it oh so many years ago
it was difficult because I didn't
understand the physics behind the tube
the tube is a negative resistance which
means
that before the laser action we fly as
it's a very high resistance once it does
fire you've got conduction through the
ionized gas so the resistance drops so
um yeah building a power supply was
doable I could build it better today
than I actually built in homemade
Holograms a big homemade Holograms use
the car ignition coil which you can
still do it I think just basically
changing uh one or two of the
transistors in that circuit and it would
be much more efficient
as far as the tube can you just go to
one of the tube makers the new on the
neon sign tube makers and have them make
something for you
no I don't think so they can't the uh
the the laser tubes themselves are very
special and the you know the Optics
keeping the mirrors have have perfectly
aligned as far as using a neon sign
Transformer probably would work but you
would probably burn out that tube or
like instantly I don't think that you
really got to watch the current going
through the tube and the manufacturer's
specifications is like two to three
milliamps and you really have to keep it
there if you start pushing like 10 to 20
milliamps which is what a neon sign
Transformer would do that tube is going
to not last very long
I'm sitting here with a 100 milliwatt
green laser that I brought with me today
I guess both of us have seen the
technology change so much and I was just
wondering if you could give some of your
thoughts on
the new diode Technologies and solid
state technology and the fact that you
can carry so much power around in your
pocket
well you know what this is what I want
to play with this is something I haven't
played with so far and something that I
do want to get into to see if these
laser diodes can really perform equally
to the gas lasers so that's something I
don't know the the little bit that I did
shoot with um
laser diodes worked but I didn't get the
right beam spread where it was just like
a small portion of the of the plate was
illuminated and the small portion that
was illuminated worked but the greater
part of the the film was not so so you
know so I needed a little work with that
but I mean when I did it I said okay it
does work and I had to work out the
Optics a little better but that again
that's many years ago and I haven't
really worked with it right now and
that's if I do anything that's where I'm
going to be doing it you sell holography
supplies to your company right right
what are some of the things that you
sell well
basically I developed a technique of
using magnets because I I wanted quick
setups quick knockdowns and using a
metal table with magnets on it and
having like the Optics connected to the
mag that's made things very easy to
align and get things set up and and
shoot and break down so that's we sell
we sell metal tables we sell that's what
we sell film and chemistry they have to
pretty much go somewhere else for that I
imagine well we saw the film oh you do
what do you what do you have
um it's not the Africa it's a it's um
BB plates that we break down into to
s'more so two two plate boxes two and a
half by two million right it's two and a
half by two and a half film
um the the uh developing chemistry we
get
um very famous company
not into Graphics
photographers formulary we use there to
set up for the developing chemistry well
I myself I use d19 and I just use the
bleach but uh so that's that's my thing
if you can find d19 out there that
that's that's the way to go I've seen
someone use d19 for reflection Holograms
which it's not recommended to use but
they were great Holograms yeah that's
all I've used yeah for all my reflection
Holograms is d19 and I've I've gotten
pretty good results with it one thing
that people may want to try that that
may not have done this is uh making life
mask models
um
where you make a life mask of a hand of
somebody's face then you could actually
shoot that life mask and it's not
pulsalography where you can actually
take a person's uh portrait but it's a
close facsimile and uh it's something
that people should consider doing would
you paint face or something or just do
the life mask and use it as is well when
you get the life mask what I usually do
is that you have a 3D mold and then what
I would do is fill that mold in with a
plaster or there's another material
hydrocal I think which is a finer grain
of material and then you have an actual
3D bus to a model of whatever you used
whether it be a hand to somebody's face
and shoot that so you're not actually
shooting the mask you're shooting which
is a negative mold you're shooting a
positive mold made from The Mask right
yeah yeah and where would someone get
materials like that any art supply store
yes lots of supply stores and look at
books because they have books on mask
making and I think a lot in the theater
industry movie making they have books on
making masks and models that that would
be very helpful yeah I'm surprised we
don't see more Holograms of uh
especially when you mentioned
I mean there's such incredible special
effects with masks and life-like type of
appearances that you would think that
you'd see some Holograms around of that
but we don't see anything I don't see
any any Holograms at all anymore
what are your plans for the future with
your company and yourself personally
um just keep going doing what I'm doing
um I am thinking about doing another
book on
holography but this will be a smaller
book than a book a simple book uh just
incorporating what I've learned over the
last 10 years 20 years playing around
with the technology and yeah trying to
give it to the students now trying to
aim aim to the high school and uh
especially with the laser pointers now
so if you can make decent Holograms with
the laser pointers which is really made
it easier to enter into the field but
but yeah
anything you'd like to tell the
listeners that we haven't covered or
that I haven't asked about no no listen
Frank is really great because he's been
wanting to interview me for years and
I'm saying well you know I really really
don't have that much to say but uh
you've done it all right and we're gonna
head out for breakfast so everyone take
care and John thank you very much very
much for being on the show all right
thanks
foreign